the same thing awaits the Russian Federation,
то же самое ждёт Российскую Федерацию
it will fight now I explain Yes, it
она будет раться сейчас объясняю Да она
will disintegrate into a national
будет распадаться на национальное
State and into a
Государство и на
regional one
региональный
Hello Hello, I’m from the city of
Здравствуйте Здравствуйте я из города
Khmelnitsky Where am I from, as you can see from
Хмельницкий Вы откуда я как вы видите из
Russia So I, too, from Russia, see the flag
России Так я тоже из России вижу флажок
is lit And which city from
светится А город какой из
Moscow I understand?  Arrived in Moscow or a
Москвы понял а в Москву Приехали или
native
коренной
Muscovite was coming
Москвич ехал
from the Moscow region I understood immediately
откуда с Московской области Понял сразу
to such questions Seriously, the map, the map of the
к таким вопросам Серьёзно что карта
collapse of the Russian Federation, this
карта распада Российской Федерации это
is interesting, this is interesting
вот это интересно вот это интересно
Tell us, there is an
Расскажите есть
organization of representatives of national
организация представителей национальных
republics who advocate
республик которые выступают за
independence for their republics and
независимой своих республик и
regions, this is interesting and you  As I
регионов это интересно и вы лет я так
understand it, you are looking from Russia for such
понимаю ищете из России вот такие вот
national minorities Yes, who would like to No, it’s
нац меньшинства Да которые бы хотели Нет
not that the point is that I’m more looking for just
не то дело в том что больше ищу просто
people and communicating with them
людей и общаюсь с ними
about the potential collapse of the Russian
о потенциальном распаде Российской
Federation, I convey the idea that every
Федерации я доношу такую идею что каждая
Empire went through a stage in the 20th century
Империя так она x-2 век проходила этап
collapse, that is, there was a period when empires
распада то есть был период Когда империи
were strengthening. At the end of the 10th beginning of the 20th century,
укреплялись Вот в конце X начале XX века
they all fell apart. The Ottoman Empire
они все сыпались Османская империя
collapsed into national
развалилась да на национальные
states, the Austro-Hungarian British
государства австро-венгерская британская
French, in fact,
французская по сути э все вот
most of the now independent
большинство сейчас независимых
states. Even 100 years ago they were in
государств Ещё лет 100 назад были в
some kind of imperial ones.  states
каких-то имперских там государствах Да
Yes, and now, for example, uh, Chile
вот и сейчас например ээ вот Чили
Argentina, they speak Spanish,
Аргентина говорят на испанском языке
the same people live there as the Spaniards are
живут там те же люди что и как Испанцы
genetically the same, but they are independent
генетически так во но они независимые
states Yes,
государства Да в Соединённые Штаты
the same British lived in the United States of America, in
Америки жили те же самые британцы по
fact, they disconnected them, they live separately, they
сути да отсоединили живут себе отдельно
speak English  language, for example,
говорят на английском языке например да
yes, the same thing awaits the Russian
вот тоже то же самое ждёт Российскую
Federation, it will fight now, I
Федерацию она будет раться сейчас
explain Yes, it will disintegrate into
объясняю Да она будет распадаться на
national states and into
национальные государства и на
regional ones. Why Because This is
региональные Почему Потому что Такова
the logic of the historical process; this
логика исторического процесса этот
process should have been completed in
процесс должен был закончен быть в 1917
1917. That is, when there was a period of spring of
году То есть когда было период весны
nations in  including in Tsarist Russia,
народов в том числе и в царской России
a revolution occurred, the
так произошла революция произошёл распад
state collapsed as an empire, Finland
государства Ээ как империи Да Финляндия
became independent, Poland, Ukraine and a
стала независимой Польша Украина и ещё
number of other states. And then Lenin
ряд других государств Да потом Ленин так
came to power and restored
пришёл ээ к власти и восстановил силовым
control over some
путём контроль над некоторыми
territories by force, in the form of the Soviet Union.
территориями так в виде Советского Союза
became the same Empire but
вот Ээ это стала та же самая Империя но
without some parts without Poland without
без некоторых частей без там Польши без
Finland and others in the ninety-
Финляндии и ещё других В девяносто
first year But the logic of the historical
первом году Но логика исторического
process is moving towards the formation of
процесса идёт Всё равно к образованию
national states, the growth of
национальных государств росту
national self-awareness, and
национального самосознания так и
the regionalist of the
регионалист
central movements, and in the first
центровых движений вот в дено первом
year the process of the collapse of the Soviet Union
году процесс распада Советского Союза
reached  to its culminating point
дошёл к своей кульминационной точке Да
Yes, I call it the second stage of the collapse of the
это называю это второй этап распада
Russian Empire Yes, it collapsed into
Российской Империи Да развалился на
large national states Yes, and
крупные национальные государства Да ээ и
now the Russian Federation remains Yes, the
сейчас осталась Российская Федерация Да
Russian Federation is an artificial
Российская Федерация - это искусственное
political formation, so it does not have a
политическое образование так у него нет
single unifying factor except uh, the
ни одного объединяющего фактора кроме
bayonets of Moscow, conditionally yes  that
как э штыки Москвы условно так да то
is, if you take away the FSB there and so on
есть если забрать там ФСБ и так дальше
Yes, tomorrow all regions will be uh
Да всё завтра все регионы будут ээ
independent yes uh If we look at the Caucasus
независимые да э Если мы смотрим Кавказ
If we look there Tatarstan
Если мы смотрим там Татарстан
Bashkartastan Sakha Yakutia yes they have a very
башкартастан Саха Якутия да у них очень
strong national identity and they
сильное национальное самосознание и они
are going to
э идут к
uh as if with a view to-  Russians are, uh,
Ээ как бы ус видом по-русски это ээ
understanding themselves as political
осмыслению себя как политическими
nations, but somewhere less, somewhere more,
нациями да где-то меньше где-то больше
for example, Tatarstan
например Татарстан ещё В девяносто
held a referendum on
втором году проводил референдум о
state sovereignty back in the ninety-second year and passed
государственном суверенитете и провёл
it. Yes, and then Yeltsin
его Да и принял потом правда Ельцин
accepted it, but he squeezed them a little.
немножко их прижал
Many of these economic republics
вот Многие эти Республики экономические
have quite good resources.  basis
имеют достаточно хорошую ресурсную базу
in order to exist everything
для того чтобы существовать все
is fine They see examples of other,
нормально Они видят э примеры других
for example, Turkic states Yes
например тюркских государств Да
Azerbaijan Independent lives prospering
Азербайджан Независимый живёт процветает
yes Kazakhstan Independent lives
да Казахстан Независимый живёт
prospering What prevents Tatarstan from also
процветать Что мешает Татарстану также
living and prospering Bashkartastan living and
жить и процветать башкартастан жить и
prospering yes, that is, for example, I
процветать да то есть я вот например
asked people from the Far East Yes,
спрашивал у людей из Дальнего Востока Да
why  Moscow gives you this is what Moscow gives you:
зачем вам Москва вот что вам даёт Москва
people from the Trans-Baikal Territory from the Far
люди с Забайкальского края с Дальнего
East have almost never been to Moscow
Востока в Москве почти никогда не были
or were sometimes sent on an excursion there
или были иногда как на экскурсию там им
from work, they went there and
с работы отправили они там походили и
nothing connects them with Moscow,
всё их не связывает ничего с Москвой
except that Moscow takes money,
Кроме того что Москва забирает деньги
resources and  people are giving coffins, that’s
ресурсы и людей от даёт гробы вот и
all I
всё я
understood, a very
понял очень
interesting
интересно оптимистичная
theory, optimistic for Ukrainian self-awareness. Well,
для украинского самосознания теория Ну
look, there’s no question here. We’re not
смотрите тут не вопрос э Мы же не
saying that this will happen tomorrow, we
говорим что это стане будет завтра мы не
can’t collapse, for example, no one could
можем распа например никто не мог
say that everything would burst there in 1917, the
сказать что там в 1917 всё лопнет
Russian Empire, no one  I could say
Российская империя никто не мог сказать
this in the ninety-first year the
так девяносто первый год развалится
Soviet Union will collapse, yes But the logic of the
Советский Союз да Но логика
historical process Well, Russia is not an
исторического процесса Ну Россия же не
Empire, it is a Federation and not an Empire, it is a Federation that is
Империя она Федерация ипе Империя она
simply formal, it is a
Федерация просто формальна это
formal Federation, a federation according to the
формальная Федерация федерация по
Constitution, look again, the Constitution is
Конституции смотрите ещё раз Конституция
not a Constitution, you understand that the
не Конституция вы понимаете что
constitution is - you will not accept this, as it
конституция - это примете не примете как
were  there you didn’t accept essentially it’s an Empire
бы там вы не приняли по сути это Империя
yes What is the essence of an empire Yes an Empire
да В чём суть империи Да Империя
You had a Federation if only yes In
Федерация у вас была б если бы да В
Yakutia Yes Sakha had its own national
Якутии Да в сахе был своё национальное
state Yes in Tatarstan you have your own
государства Да в Татарстане своё у вас
in fact they only have the formal
фактически они имеют только формальный
status of republics Yes what’s the point
статус республик Да в чём в чём
federalism money is taken by everyone yes What is
федерализм деньги забирают все да В чём
federalism firstly firstly in
федерализм во-первых во-первых в
regional languages ​​for
региональных языках для
starters what in regional languages ​​Well what
начала что в региональных языках Ну что
in each region uh at the administrative
в каждом регионе э на административном
level they can use uh the regional
уровне могут использовать э региональный
language can in fact in fact How
язык могут по факту по факту Сколько
many schools in Bashkortostan with Bashkor
сколько в Башкортостане школ с башкор
Skim  language of education I will tell you statistics
Ским языком обучения статистику вам
now, I am sure that I am sure that
сейчас назову я уверен что я уверен что
you are prepared with the guys from also
вы подготовлены вот с ребятами из тоже
no yes in Tatarstan there are several schools
нет да в Татарстане есть несколько школ
there is a gymnasium and even then they are trying to close them in
там гимназия Да и то их пытаются закрыть
Dagestan there is in Chechnya in Dagestan in
Дагестане есть в Чечне в Дагестане на
what language the school is there Dana is in Chechnya
каком языке школа есть Дане есть в Чечне
is  Do you know how many nationalities there are
есть А вы знаете Сколько национальностей
in Dagestan, I don’t know, there are Avars,
в Дагестане не не знаю там аварцы
Dargins, Kumyks, Lak
даргинцы кумыки лак
Tabasaran, there are a lot of them. Well, there
табасаран там очень много Ну десяток
are definitely a dozen different ones, yes, yes,
точно есть разных да да
no, look, 48 - this can already be considered that way, you
вот Нет смотрите 48 - это уже можно так
know, just like they say in
считать знаете так же как говорят в
Russia, there are 200 nationalities. If there
России там 200 национальностей Если двое
are two people  more in Russia more than
человек есть больше в России больше чем
this look like this and in Ukraine Then
так смотри так так и в Украине Тогда
more than 200 like this in any country you
больше чем 200 так так в любой стране вы
Take any country in it more than
Возьмите любую страну в ней больше чем
200 more than
200 больше чем
200 more than 200 look in Odessa alone
200 больше чем 200 смотри в одной Одессе
Damn there are 100 nationalities on
блин там национальностей 100 есть на
import and on the market  this is a clometer What
привозе и на рынке сеь клометр Какие
nationalities are they all What And tell me what
национальности все Какие А скажите какая
nationality is there in Russia, not
национальность которая есть в России нет
in
в
Ukraine No, it’s just
Украине Не ну это
like that when you say 200
вот так вот тогда когда вы говорите 200
there are some nationalities I’m talking
там с чем-то национальности Я же говорю
about the number, you understand Let’s
про количество понимаете Давайте
go back to your map,
вернёмся лучше к вашей карте
it’s interesting, it’s interesting  So
занимательно это интересно Так вот
look, let’s take for example about the
смотрите возьмём например про
national Republics, it’s simple,
национальные Республики тут просто да у
they have a national identity, they have a
них есть национальное самосознание у них
separate identification as a linguistic
отдельная идентификация как языковая
religious one. Yes, this is a very strong factor. Yes,
религиозная Да это очень сильный фактор
everything is clear with them, it’s more
Да с ними вообще всё понятно тут
interesting why, for example, Siberia or the
интереснее зачем например Сибири или
Far East are not so protected from
Дальнему Востоку не замость так от
Moscow. That’s because  many people say, Well,
Москвы Вот потому что многие говорят Ну
why do I need independence? I’m Russian, and I’m
зачем мне независимость я же русский и
Russian there in Moscow. Yes, here’s something else, and
там в Москве русский Да вот тут другое и
here regional identity comes in,
тут вступает региональная идентичность
for example, people who live like this in the Urals and
например люди которые на Урале так живут
Siberians in Siberia, they have completely different
и в Сибири сибиряки у них совсем разная
regional identities, and those Urals
региональная идентичность да те уральцы
say those Siberians. That’s how they are  and
говорят те сибиряки Вот они прямо так и
we call them Siberians, that is, there is a
называют мы сибиряки то есть есть
certain identity formed
определённая идентичность сформированная
there, there is also the Jewish Autonomous
там ещё есть Еврейская автономная
Republic, the Jewish Autonomous Region, a
республика Еврейская автономная область
region, in my opinion, if I’m not mistaken, the
область она по-моему Если не ошибаюсь
region Yes, this is an artificial formation
область Да это искусственное образование
Yes, Stalin then the Jewish population
Да Сталин тогда там еврейского население
there is about 10%, if not less Yes, and it’s good for
там около 10% если не меньше Да и оно ну
you  Listen, everything is artificial in general,
вас Послушай так всё искусственно вообще
the country is so real. Where did the
страна так оно ну реально Откуда Там
Jews come from? They took Stalin or whoever
взялась еврейская взяли Сталин или кто
decided everything needed to be done; they did
там решил всё надо сделали
Birabidzhan; they sent them there and everything, that is, the Jews who
Бирабиджан отправили их туда и всё то
want to look at the Jews
есть евреев которые хотят смотрите евреи
who want to come to Israel. I know
которые хотят приехать в Израиль Я знаю
Jews who want to go to the
евреи которые хотят при ехать в
Jewish.  autonomous region I don’t know,
еврейскую автономную область Я не знаю
therefore there is
поэтому национального как бы такого
no national identity there, yes, that is, this is the
идентичности там нету да то есть это
territory in which they live there,
территория на которой они там живут
some of whom were sent there Under the
некоторые которых прислали туда При
Soviet Union, yes How will it be I
Советском Союзе да Каким образом будет я
heard Well, I also have a question for you, you
услышал Ну у меня тоже есть к вам вопрос
see How the implementation will take place
видите Каким образом будет происходить
this map, it will be
реализация вот этой карты это будет
some kind of big revolution, people will come
какая-то большая революция люди выедут
to the square, the question is how the
на площади вопрос вопрос в том как будет
Russian Empire will end its days.
заканчивать свои дни Российская империя
Yes, this is in the third phase, yes. Well,
Да вот это в третьей фазе это да Ну
now it is called the Federation when
сейчас она называется Федерация когда
it called the Soviet Union. But this
она называ Советский Союз Но это по сути
was essentially in its own way  The spirit was all the
было по своему Дух это всё было
Russian Empire Yes, and Ukraine was
Российская империя Да а Украина была
part of the Russians, part of the Russian Yes, part of the
частью россий частью да Российской Да
Russian Empire, of course, and
частью Российской империи конечно да и
Finland was part of Poland was
Финляндия была частью часть Польши была
part of the Russian Empire Finland was not
частью Российской империи Финляндия не
part of the Russian Empire, only a
была частью Российской империи только
small piece of Findi Well, a
кусочек неболь кусочек финди Ну таки
piece of Ukraine was not all of Ukraine  was
кусочек Украины был не вся Украина была
in the Russian Empire Well, about
в Российской империи Ну порядка
80% no no far from 80% not what are you
80% нет нет далеко не 80% не вы что
looking at eh all no Lviv region
смотрите э вся нет Львовская область
Ivano-Frankivsk Transcarpathian
ивано-франковская Закарпатская
Chernivtsi there was no
Черновицкая вообще не было в Российской
Ivano-Frankivsk in the Russian Empire Well how was it not
ивано-франковска Ну как это не было
Ternopil why was it
Тернопольская почему это было
Ternopil border Well I  I live in the
Тернопольская граница Ну я живу в
Khmelnitsky region, we have a neighboring
Хмельницкой области у нас э соседняя
Ternopil region along the river with a bruch. It
Тернопольская область по речке с бруч
was until the year thirty-nine.
было Э до тридцать девятого года
Maybe I’m wrong. But in the thirty-
было Может я ошибаюсь Но тридцать
ninth year the Soviet Union
девятом году Советский Союз когда
captured Poland. Yes, the
захватил Польшу Да вот
modern Ternopil region was
Тернопольская область современная была в
part of Poland only in the year three and nine the
составе Польши только в три девятом году
Soviets came there  and central Ukraine
советы туда пришли а центральная Украина
Central Ukraine Yes, it was part of the
Центральная Украина Да входила в часть в
Russian Empire and Eastern Ukraine
Российскую империю а Восточная Украина
Eastern Ukraine Well, the east of Ukraine
Восточная Украина Ну восток Украины
East Ukraine exists vi Not the
Восток Украина имеется ви Не восточ
east, yes it was part of the Russian
восток да входил в состав Российской
Empire, even more I will say Ukrainian
империи даже больше скажу украинские
ethnic territories such as Kuban
этнические территории такие как Кубань
Starodub siina type yes they were also
Стародуб сиина типа да тоже входили в
part of  Russian Empire and remained
состав Российской империи и остались в
part of the modern Russian Federation.
составе Российской Федерации современной
So what did I say incorrectly then?
Так что же я тогда сказал некорректно
70% of Ukraine is part of Russia, not you. You
70% Украины в составе Росси не вы же
say modern Ukraine, we look at
Говорите Украину современную мы смотрим
Ukraine as a
Украину как
state. Well, the 80s about it wasn’t included,
государство Да ну 80 е про не входило
it was definitely less included, yes, yes,
меньше входило это однозначно меньше
but  this is not the essence of the
входило да ну да но это не есть суть
dispute Yes, now, well, there are 70 the essence of the dispute, an
спора Да сейчас ну там 70 суть спора
entertaining map. This is the essence of the dispute,
карта занимательная Вот это суть спора
look now about the reasons, more precisely,
вот смотрите теперь э о причинах точнее
how it will disintegrate in 90; this
как будет распадаться в 90 это в 1917
was an armed rebellion in Petrograd in 1917, so that is,
был вооружённый мятеж в Петрограде так
in 1917, yes, that is, contradictions in the
то есть в 1917 да то есть противоречия в
Russian Empire  came to the conclusion that it
Российской империи пришли к тому что оно
grew into an armed struggle against the
переросло в вооружён ную борьбу против
Central government, and that is,
Центральной власти да то есть
contradictions accumulated first in
противоречия накопились сначала в 905
905 there was the First Russian Revolution. Yes,
году была Первая Русская революция Да
when the execution of this Tsar’s execution of
когда расстрел вот этот Царский расстрел
the demonstration was there for 2 years,
демонстрации был вот там 2 года полыхал
it was blazing with revolutionary events then they
это революционные события потом их
were strangled and in 917  it died down again
душили и вот в 917 оно выкс нулась снова
when the Soviet Union collapsed, it
как развалился Советский Союз он
fell apart in a slightly different scenario,
немножко по-другому сценарию развалился
that is, it was not in the center, there was something against
да то есть был не в центре что-то против
the authorities, well, like not a bunch, but there the authorities were
власти пуч Ну типа не пуч а там власть
overthrown, and the regions began to go for
свергать а регионы начали э идти на
independence first, a country ball, damn
независимость сначала страный бал блин
such an interesting interlocutor
такой интересный собеседник
ran away from the lecture, didn’t finish reading it, subscribe to
убежал лекцию не дочитал подпишись на
my Telegram right now, axis vin and popk,
мий Telegram прямо зараз ось вин а попк
more and more
це дуже и дуже
politely
важливо